# Viren Khandal

Portfolio: virenkhandal.github.io Email: virenkhandal@berkeley.edu Github: github.com/virenkhandal Mobile: +1-510-386-6222

### Summary

With over 3 years of relevant work experience in software development and machine learning through my full-time work and internships (Berkeley Research, Open Networking Foundation, Hirebee.ai, Employers4Change, etc), I have experience working on various computer vision, natural language processing, and machine learning projects, as well as developing multi-platform applications.

#### EDUCATION

#### University of Berkeley, California

Berkeley, California

Bachelor of Arts - Computer Science & Applied Mathematics (Double Major)

Aug 2019 - May 2022

Specialization: Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence

Courses: Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Efficient Algorithms, Data Structures, Modern Statistical and Predictive Analysis, Numerical, Real, and Complex Analysis, Advanced Linear Algebra, Abstract Algebra

#### Stanford University, California

Palo Alto, California

Bachelor of Arts - Computer Science

May 2018 - Sept 2018

Courses: Data Mining and Analysis, Client Side Internet Technologies

# SKILLS SUMMARY

• Languages: Python, JAVA, C, C++, JavaScript, Go, SQL, Julia

Frameworks: Tensorflow, PyTorch, Keras, Flask, NLTK, SpaCy, NodeJS, ReactJS
Tools: GIT, Unity, Docker, Shell, AWS, Azure, GCP, IBM Cloud, Arduino

• Soft Skills: Leadership, Communication, Time Management, Public Speaking, Teamwork

#### EXPERIENCE

#### UC Berkeley College of Engineering - VeHICal

Berkeley, CA

Research Engineer

May 2022 - Present

- o Mentors: Professor Sanjit Seshia, Professor Bjoern Hartmann, Dr. Balasaravanan Thoravi Kumaravel
- **Scope**: Formalizing models for safe autonomous-to-human perception handoffs in autonomous vehicles on the VeHICal project (https://vehical.org)
- **Description**: Leading project to optimize human performance in human-autonomy handoffs in autonomous driving, Developing Virtual Reality (VR) tools to conduct human-in-the-loop experiments with high ecological validity
- Research Foci: Human-Autonomy Interaction, Autonomous Driving, Virtual-Reality Development, and Machine Learning

### Stanford University - Autononous Systems Lab

Stanford, CA

Researcher

Sept 2022 - Present

- o Mentors: Professor Marco Pavone
- Scope: Investigating the effects of Out-of-Distribution events on human-autonomy interaction in autonomous driving (https://stanfordasl.github.io/)
- **Description**: Leading project to develop a framework to enable safe control handoffs in autonomous driving from vehicle to human in the case of Out-of-Distribution (OOD) events.
- o Research Foci: Human-Autonomy Interaction, Autonomous Driving, Machine Learning, and Uncertainty Learning

Postbox Remote

Full-Stack Software Engineer

June 2022 - Oct 2022

- o Mentor: Sherman Dickman
- o Scope: Personalized desktop email client, news client, and feed reader for macOS and Windows
- **Description**: Leading effort to upscale platform for optimized performance on new macOS and Windows updates, Improve automation and maintenance of CI/CD pipeline

genei.io Remote

Machine Learning Engineer

June 2022 - Aug 2022

• Mentors: Thomas Foster, Jack Bowen

- Scope: Optimized web application and extension for faster researching by automatically summarizing background reading and produce blogs, articles, and reports faster
- **Description**: Lead Document Layout Analysis project to parse the underlying structure of a PDF to categorize sections into classes and extract reading order of the text, Implemented Transformer models (LayoutLMv3 and LayoutReader) to perform scalable document layout analysis

### UC Berkeley College of Engineering - VeHICal

Student Researcher May 2021 - May 2022

- o Mentors: Professor Sanjit Seshia, Professor Bjoern Hartmann, Dr. Yash Vardhan Pant
- Scope: Formalizing models for safe autonomous-to-human perception handoffs in autonomous vehicles on the VeHICal project (https://vehical.org)
- **Description**: Improving responsibility of autonomous vehicles through verification of perception decision making by developing unique scoring metric to gauge credibility of reinforcement learning/object detection models (YOLOv3, SSD, RetinaNet)
- o Research Foci: Human-Autonomy Interaction, Robust Perception, Formal Methods

# Computer Science Mentors

Berkeley, CA

Berkeley, CA

Jan 2020 - Present

Instructor & Coordinator & Advisor

- o Mentors: Professor John DeNero, Professor Christopher Hunn
- o Scope: Lead weekly tutoring session to teach students about linear algebra, circuit analysis, and machine learning.
- Description: Lead a group of 25+ mentors by hosting teaching workshops and promoting a passion for teaching.
- Impact: Providing group tutoring for Electrical Engineering & Computer Science (EECS) courses at UC Berkeley to 2000+ undergraduate students.

Hirebee.ai Remote

Machine Learning Intern

Jan 2021 - June 2021

- o Mentors: Dr. Vahe Tshitoyan, Mrs. Luiza Avetisyan
- Scope: Streamlining the HR process by developing NLP-based algorithms for job similarity and candidate progression.
- **Description**: Designed and deployed a multilayered CNN based on Named-Entity-Recognition (NER) to extract categorized skills from resumes and job postings with 95% precision

InternPursuit Remote

Machine Learning Intern

Jan 2021 - June 2021

- o Mentors: Dr. Isabella Johnston, Mr. Irving Chin
- o Scope: Employer platform to manage intern from recruitment to exit. Learning Academy for Employers
- **Description**: Developing a novel optimization and multilayered clustering algorithm to optimally match student and employer profiles

# Cool Climate Networks

Lead Researcher

Berkeley, CA

- M + D Clit l I D D : LIV

Jan 2020 - June 2021

- Mentor: Dr. Christopher Jones, Dr. Daniel Kammen
- Scope: Research consortium at the University of California, Berkeley focused on research in developing cutting-edge carbon footprint management tools for communities in the U.S. and Internationally.
- o **Description**: Used machine learning tools in R and Python to perform qualitative/quantitative analysis and create analytical maps from US Census Tract data

What Else.io Berkeley, CA

Backend Development Intern

Sept 2019 - Feb 2020

- o **Mentor**: Mr. Pooran Prasad Rajanna
- Scope: A business productivity solution, which saves customer-oriented teams many hours, from searching data in various applications, by providing relevant content when necessary
- Description: Utilized Flask and Jinja to create an interactive Python-based web dashboard and demoed it to 100+ VC firms and investors at official Berkeley SkyDeck Demo Day

# **Open Networking Foundation**

Menlo Park, CA

June 2018 - Dec 2019

 $Software\ Engineering\ Intern$ 

- o Mentors: Dr. Guru Parulkar, Mr. William Snow, Mr. Matteo Scandolo
- Scope: Operator Led Consortium hosting open source mobile broadband projects driving network industry transformation
- $\circ$  **Description**: Development/Unit testing work to enhance UI for key Internet Service Providers with JavaScript, jQuery, and AJAX

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Academic Paper: Human-in-the-Loop Control Handoffs in Out-of-Distribution (OOD) Contexts: A framework to enable safe control handoffs in autonomous driving from vehicle to human in the case of Out-of-Distribution (OOD) events. Tech: Python, Tensorflow, TinyYolo (In Progress) Submitting to the International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) 2023
- Academic Paper: Learning-Driven Oracle-Guided Compositional Symbiotic Design of Cyber-Physical Systems (LOGiCS): Developing a control system for Underwater Autonomous Vehicles (UAVs) to safely maneuver around land and drop off payload. Tech: Python, Control Theory, Physics (In Progress) DARPA Funded Project
- Academic Paper: Using Immersive Virtual Reality to Improve the Realism of Perception Handoff Testing for Safer Autonomous Driving: An immersive human-in-the-loop virtual reality autonomous driving simulation to increase the realism and efficacy of existing perception handoff testing. Tech: Virtual Reality, Unity, C++, Python (September '22) Submitted to ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) 2023
- Academic Workshop Paper: Exploring Credibility Scoring Metrics of Perception Systems for Autonomous Driving: An empirical study on the reliability of object detectors and their points of failure based on realistic, non-adversarial perturbations. Tech: Python, Tensorflow, TinyYolo, GCP (December '21) Accepted at IEEE/ACM COMSNETS Intelligent Transportation Systems 2022
- Academic Paper: Modeling the 15 Tile Puzzle Through the Lens of Group Theory: Developing a mathematical backing for the 15 Tile Puzzle and solving strategies using group and ring theory. (November '21) Self-Publish
- Publication: Consumption Based Greenhouse Gas Inventory of San Francisco from 1990 to 2015: A consumption-based emissions inventory for the City/County of San Francisco, California from 1990 to 2015. Tech: R, Python, Data Analysis (October '20) Presented at Commission on the Environment San Francisco
- Industry Conference Paper: Determining the Causalities of Network Delay and Latency: An approach using a correlation analysis and machine learning to determine the constituents of network latency. Tech: Python, R, Tensorflow, Keras (September '19) Presented at ONF Connect 2019
- Industry Conference Paper: The Beginnings of a Search Engine: An introductory model for a search engine, built on search optimization through a variety of classifiers (SVMs, Random Forests, etc). Tech: Python, R, TensorFlow, PyTorch (December '18) Presented at ONF Connect 2018

#### Projects

- Virtual Reality Autonomous Driving Simulation (VRADS): A high-fidelity VR simulation to realistically model and influence human attentiveness in autonomous driving contexts. Tech: Unity, C++, OpenXR (August '22)
- Drowsiness Detection System (Computer Vision, Machine Learning): AI model to detect/prevent drowsiness in autonomous vehicles. Tech: DeepLearning4Java, OpenCV, Tensorflow, Android Studio (August '21)
- Wrapt (Full-Stack, RESTful API): Web Application for visualizing Spotify listening activity with Spotify, Twitter, and Instagram integration. Tech: Python, Flask, JavaScript, API Integration (February '21)
- MoodMatch multimedia recommendation system (Machine Learning, NLP, Full-Stack, Web Crawlers): Multi-platform application for recommending trending music/movies based on user's mood using novel sentimental analysis algorithms. Tech: Python, NodeJS, NLTK, TensorFlow, Keras, Azure (October '20)
- BeachBuddy multimedia recommendation system (Machine Learning, RESTful API, Full-Stack, Web Crawlers): Multi-platform application for recommending beaches based on several criteria (crowd, weather, distance, etc) using novel clustering algorithm built on PyTorch. Tech: Python, PyTorch, AWS, Flask (July '20)

# Honors & Awards

- Amazon Web Services Cloud Practitioner In Progress
- First Place Winner at Global DefHacks Hackathon July, 2020
- Awarded title of Computer Science Scholar at University of California, Berkeley Sept, 2019
- Second Place Winner at Global Amazon Web Services Hackathon, May, 2019